Yoonsu Kim

Ph.D. Student | HCI Researcher

☑ yoonsu16@kaist.ac.kr | kysoo816@gmail.com 🏠 https://yoonsu0816.github.io/

Research Interests

My research interests include around **Human-Computer Interaction**, **Human-Centered AI**, and **Human-AI** collaboration.

I am passionate about developing new interactions and systems that help people better utilize AI technology and understand the difficulties in using or trying to use it.

Education

KAIST

Ph.D. in School of Computing

Advisor: <u>Juho Kim</u>

KAIST

M.S. in AI (Specialization: Human-AI Interaction)

Advisor: Juho Kim

POSTECH

B.S. in Computer Science and Engineering

Magna cum laude

Feb 2024 - Present

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Feb 2022 - Feb 2024

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Feb 2017 - Feb 2022

Pohang, Republic of Korea

Publications

Conferences and Journal Papers

[C1] Understanding Users' Dissatisfaction with ChatGPT Responses: Types, Resolving Tactics, and the Effect of Knowledge Level

Yoonsu Kim, Jueon Lee, Seoyoung Kim, Jaehyuk Park, Juho Kim *ACM Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI 2024)*

[C2] AI-to-Human Actuation: AI Proactively Induces Humans towards Favorable Sensing Conditions

Sungjae Cho, **Yoonsu Kim**, Jaewoong Jang, Inseok Hwang *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT 2023)*.

Posters, Demos, and Workshop Papers

[D1] RECIPE: How to Integrate ChatGPT into EFL Writing Education

Sungjae Cho, **Yoonsu Kim**, Jaewoong Jang, Inseok Hwang

Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT 2023).

Last updated: April 30, 2024

[D2] Towards Understanding the Challenges and Remedies in AI Application Development Dae Hyun Kim*, Yoonsu Kim*, Hyungyu Shin, Jinho Son, Juho Kim (* Corresponding authors) Korea Computer Congress 2023 (KCC 2023)

[D3] Demonstrating AHA: Boosting Unmodified AI's Robustness by Proactively Inducing Favorable Human Sensing Conditions

Sungjae Cho, Jaewoong Jang, **Yoonsu Kim**, Inseok Hwang Adjunct Proceedings of the 2023 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing & the 2023 ACM International Symposium on Wearable Computing (UbiComp/ISWC '23 Adjunct)

Experiences

HIS Lab (Human-Centered Intelligent System Lab in POSTECH)

Jun 2021 - Feb 2022

Research Intern

Pohang, Republic of Korea

Human-Computer Interaction, Human-AI Interaction, Embedded AI System

NAVER Connect Foundation

Feb 2020 - Feb 2021

Manager of boostcamp

Seoul, Republic of Korea

Web & Mobile, AI Software Education

Neuromeka

Software Development Intern

Jun 2019 - Aug 2019

Android application development for robot manipulation

and robot database management

Pohang, Republic of Korea

Samsung Electronics Co.

Research Intern

Jan 2019 - Feb 2019

Department of Visual Display, AI • Big Data Lab

Suwon, Republic of Korea

SK Telecom

Software Development Intern

Jun 2018 - Aug 2018

Department of Service Platform

Seoul, Republic of Korea

AI Technology Unit, Knowledge and Technology Cell

Scholarship

National Scholarship (Science and Engineering)

2017 - 2023

Global Leadership Program

Mar 2018 - Feb 2020

Samsung Dream Class Scholarship

Jan. 2018 ~ Feb. 2018

Leadership & Service

Leadership

KAIST-Google exploreCSR

Mar 2023 - Present

Student Organizer

POSTECH Student Council

Feb 2019 - Feb 2021

Director of Welfare Department

Last updated: April 30, 2024

POSTECH Library Council

President, Vice President Mar 2017 - Aug 2019

POSTECH Reader's Club 6

(Awarded by Excellent Mentee) Feb 2019 - Dec 2018

POSTECH Reader's Club 5

Teaching

POSTECH Programming and Problem Solving (CSED101)

Teaching Mentor Feb 2021 - Dec 2021

Volunteering

KOICA WFK Korean Medicine Volunteer Group Overseas Medical Dec 2023

Volunteer ActivitiesKrong Battambang,
Cambodia

KOICA WFK Korean Medicine Volunteer Group Overseas Medical Aug 2019

Volunteer Activities Toshken, Uzbekistan